Guide to the N. Scott Momaday Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Papers, 1788-2012; 1950s-2012
  - Carlisle research on students. This folder contains information on Juan Herrera, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Carlisle research on students. This folder contains information on Nina Hicks, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Carlisle research on students. This folder contains information on Nellie Holycloud, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Carlisle research on students. This folder contains information on Eva Jones, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Carlisle research on students. This folder contains information on Hannah Kennedy, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Carlisle research on students. This folder contains information on Titeresa Lay, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Carlisle research on students. This folder contains information on Lucy Lenoir, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Carlisle research on students. This folder contains information on Blanche McLaughlin, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Carlisle research on students. This folder contains information on Thomas Miles, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Carlisle research on students. This folder contains information on Sylvia Moon, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Carlisle research on students. This folder contains information on Julia Perrine, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Carlisle research on students. This folder contains information on Florence Perrine, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Carlisle research on students. This folder contains information on Margaret Pickett, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Carlisle research on students. This folder contains information on Mary Shomin, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Carlisle research on students. This folder contains information on Josephine Skenadore, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Carlisle research on students. This folder contains information on William Dietz, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Carlisle research on students. This folder contains information on Reo Spicer, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Carlisle research on students. This folder contains information on Thomas Standing, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Carlisle research on students. This folder contains information on Lucinda Welch, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Carlisle research on students. This folder contains information on Agnes White, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Carlisle research on students. This folder contains information on Ethel Williams, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Carlisle research on students. This folder contains information on Elizabeth Wind, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Carlisle research on students. This folder contains information on Wilson Silas, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Carlisle research on students. This folder contains information on Joseph Wilson, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Carlisle research on students. This folder contains information on Louis Plante, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Carlisle research on students. This folder contains information on Della Smith, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Carlisle research on students. This folder contains information on Hattie Snow, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Carlisle research on students. This folder contains information on Louise Spott, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Carlisle research on students. This folder contains information on Minnie Akkaum, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Carlisle research on students. This folder contains information on Muryel Springo, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Carlisle research on students. This folder contains information on Louise Stricker, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Carlisle research on students. This folder contains information on William Thomas, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Carlisle research on students. This folder contains information on Patrick Verney, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Carlisle research on students. This folder contains information on Catherine Vornwald, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Carlisle research on students. This folder contains information on Daphe Waggoner, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Carlisle research on students. This folder contains information on Eva Walterman, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Carlisle research on students. This folder contains information on Delia Edwards, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Carlisle research on students. This folder contains information on Gertrude Bressette, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Photocopy of Carlisle yearbook, 1917, circa 1910s (Box 8)
  - Photocopy of a sketch called "How Carlisle Feel To Day", circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Carlisle research on students. This folder contains information on Mary Wilmer, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Carlisle outing form with rules, signed by John Mohawk 1900, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Carlisle research on students. This folder contains information on Anna Gouituey, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Carlisle research on students. This folder contains information on Sadie Metoxen, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Carlisle research on students. This folder contains information on Minnie Tsait-Kopeta, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Forms and the Carlisle Arrow photocopies, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Carlisle research on students. This folder contains information on Alex Arcasa, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Carlisle research on students. This folder contains information on Joseph Bergie, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Carlisle research on students. This folder contains information on Elmes Busch, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Carlisle research on students. This folder contains information on Joseph Guyon, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Carlisle research on students. This folder contains information on Peter and Georgia Calac Mission, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Carlisle research on students. This folder contains information on Pete Calac, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Carlisle research on students. This folder contains information on Jim Thorpe, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Carlisle research on students. This folder contains information on Gus Welch, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Carlisle research on students. This folder contains information on Frank Hudson, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Carlisle research on students. This folder contains information on Hazel Myers, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Carlisle research on students. This folder contains information on Joseph Muggins, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Carlisle research on students. This folder contains information on John Bear, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Photocopy of a photo of "Ford's apprenticeship program at Highland Park, Mich. Participants pictured., undated (Box 8)
  - Photocopy of newspaper (from Carlisle?) Vol. #10 May 1885, pg. 8 listing correspondence between students and their parents, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Research on Carlisle, including "The Hessian Powder Magazine: Preserving the heritage and history of the Carlisle Barracks"; "Historic Carlisle Barracks"; "National Museum of the American Indian Spring 2000"; card reminder to attend Remembering Carlisle Indian School May 26, 2000; "Experience Carlisle, Pennsylvania"; "The Carlisle Indian Industrial School; "Central PA", circa 2000s (Box 8)
  - Research on Carlisle, including photocopies of historic newspapers, correspondence with Genevieve Bell about research on Carlisle; photocopy of the athletic celebration program from 1912; Photocopy of A Cheyenne Sketchbook by Cohoe; photograph of a panoramic view of campus; photograph of an unidentified student; photograph on nurses, photographs of unidentified students in an envelope; support board, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Drafts of The Moon in Two Windows with notes for chages and editing, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Travel information including airline mileage summary, airline tickets, hotel receipts from travel during the 1996 year, including a trip to Spain, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Bank statements and un-cashed checks signed by NSM all from 1996, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Car maintenance statements and fuel receipts from 1996, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Prescription receipts from 1996, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Receipts for business supplies and miscellaneous expenses in 1996, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Royalty Statements from 1996, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Receipts and statements relating to household and studio expenses in 1996, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Correspondence between NSM and Sarah Feldman at Joshua Morris Publishing Inc. regarding the publication of a number of stories including "How the Rock Tree Came to Be". Appears the title of the work was to be "A Treasury of Native American Stories for Children" to be published in 1994, but there are no signs it was ever published., circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Photocopies of media coverage of NSM and his work in 1996, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Correspondence between NSM and Insignia Films regarding a project called The West 1995, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Correspondence regarding a presentation by NSM at the Ethnicity and the Problem of Multicultural Identity: Where do You Come From, Where Do You Go? Conference at the University of Oregon, May 1997, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Correspondence related to a Citizen Book Project which will include a chapter by NSM, 1996; "The Pullet Who Bit the Bullet" by NSM (The chapter for the book project); Letter from University of Arizona about publishing the NSM Collector's Edition of House Made of Dawn, The Way to Rainy Mountain, and The Names, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Letter from NSM nominating Anna Curtenius Roosevelt for the American Academy of Achievement Golden Plate Award, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Correspondence regarding presentations by NSM and the American College Health Association and Winslow High School, 1996, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Correspondence between NSM and Olivier Delavault regarding the Saint-Malo Book Fair in May, 1997., circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Maureen Shannon Salzer Reading List for Preliminary Examination (NSM The Way to Rainy Mountain is on the list), circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - "Hugh Scott's 1931 film on Indian Sign Language" VHS tape; Paper by Melanie McKay-Cody "Preserving the Native American Heritage: Indian Sign Language"; Letter to Melanie McKay-Cody from NSM regarding Kiowa sign language; Article by H.L. Scott, "Sign Language of the Plains Indian"; Handwritten letter to NSM from Melanie McKay-Cody regarding the, circa 1930s (Box 8)
  - Correspondence regarding the Pasadena City College Visiting Scholar program, 1994-1995, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Correspondence with Manuel Villar Raso regarding a trip to Spain in January 1996; A photocopied article, "The Glamour of Delinquency"; Rhett Darby's "The Novelist as Lawyer: Advocating of Counterstorytelling the Dialectical Indian in Linda Hogan's Mean Spirit, circa 1990s (Box 8)
  - Research on the Osage Murders in the early 1920s including photocopies of media coverage, testimonies and police reports, circa 1920s (Box 9)
  - Letters from Jon Simon Guggenheim Memorial Foundation asking NSM to respond regarding a candidate for a fellowship through the organization; Letters from Emory and Henry College regarding NSM availability for and appearance; Manuscript of Children of the Sun by NSM; Article "So You Want to Win A Nobel Prize", undated (Box 9)
  - Multiple photocopies of NSM passport; "Opening the Shawl" by Susan Scarberry-Garcia; A Letter to Navajo/Apache Tribal Council Delegates, February 24, 1997; Forms and paperwork from Navajo Prep regarding a trip to Russia, circa 1990s (Box 9)
  - "A Dark, Indifferent Rage" by NSM; Directory of the University of Arizona Department of English; Spain addresses and Contact information; Correspondence regarding a trip to Spain in January 1996, circa 1990s (Box 9)
  - Course information for classes NSM taught in 1994-95 including rosters, grades, textbook requests, and syllabi, circa 1990s (Box 9)
  - Articles on the Osage murders, circa 1990s (Box 9)
  - School of American Research letter regarding a donation of paintings by NSM; Listing or participants in "Place, Expression, and Experience" March 27-April 2 1993 at the School of American Research, Santa Fe, circa 1990s (Box 9)
  - Letter from Ruth Frazier to the Board of Directors of Futures for Children and other information on the organization, undated (Box 9)
  - Letter and invitation to a dinner and board meeting for the Ohio University Museum of American art. 1993, circa 1990s (Box 9)
  - Wings of America: American Indian Youth Development Programs with NSM on the honorary council, 1992, circa 1990s (Box 9)
  - Letter to Marilyn Poutier of the Native American Rights Fund informing her that NSM will be unable to visit May 7-8 1993, circa 1990s (Box 9)
  - Invitation to NSM to participate in the Global Forum General Assembly in Kyoto, Japan April 20-23 1993, circa 1990s (Box 9)
  - Note to NSM from Herschel Sahmaunt, Kiowa Tribe of Oklahoma Tribal Chairman dated August 6, 1993; Kiowa Gourd Clan 1995 Schedule of Events; Kiowa Gourd Clan 1994 Schedule of Events; Letter to Pat from NSM, 1994, circa 1990s (Box 9)
  - Grand Canyon Trust papers: Board of Trustees Meeting Minutes, Memorandums, Board Tasks and Assignments, List of the Board of trustees; Informational packets and correspondence from 1993-1995, circa 1990s (Box 9)
  - Pamphlets and brochures from Institute of American Indian Arts Foundation in Santa Fe, with NSM as the Honorary Chair it 1994. Booklets include: "Sayday was Coming Along: Silverhorns Drawings of the Kiowa Trickster"; "A Gathering of Shield", circa 1990s (Box 9)
  - Letters from "The Players" regarding NSM membership in the organization, 1995, circa 1990s (Box 9)
  - American Academy of the Arts and Sciences Western Center Membership Directory 1992-1993; Booklet of information about the organization, a listing of new members in 1993, and letters regarding dues and events, circa 1990s (Box 9)
  - Haskell Indian Junior College Foundation papers, including the Monthly Financial Report for Feb. 1994; Board of trustees meeting information, 1994; informational booklet, and correspondence, circa 1990s (Box 9)
  - The MacArthur Fellows Program: Some Frequently Asked Questions booklet; Letter from NSM saying he is delighted to serve as the nominator in the MacArthur Fellows Program 1994; The MacArthur Fellows Program annual report for 1992 and report on activities for 1992; plus correspondence, circa 1990s (Box 9)
  - Some People Need Killing a screenplay by Meir Z. Ribalow, copyright 1996. Copy, circa 1990s (Box 9)
  - Chains of Love a screenplay by Meir Z. Ribalow, copyright 1996. Copy, circa 1990s (Box 9)
  - Ghost Man: Essays by Tom Simmons copyright 1997, spiral bound copy, circa 1990s (Box 9)
  - For Better of Worse by Bernard Pomerance, circa 1990s (Box 9)
  - Genevieve Bell's dissertation Telling Stories Out of School: Remembering the Carlisle Indian Industrial School, 1879-1918 with a note attached to NSM and Rachel dated 6/12/98, circa 1990s (Box 9)
  - The Buffalo Trust letterhead with NSM as Founder and Chairman, undated (Box 9)
  - Preface to The Way to Rainy Mountain attached to two short stories by Barbara Kingsolver, undated (Box 9)
  - Permissions and licensees for the Smithsonian Institution to reproduce NSM work, a poem "Carriers of the Dream Wheel" from The Guard Dancer to be included in Native Universe by the Smithsonian Institution; "The Testimony of Allan Houser" by NSM drafts and agreements for the Smithsonian Institution; Chronology of Allan Houser's work and awards; Photocopies of pictures of Allan Houser's art., undated (Box 9)
  - Forward by NSM to "The Way of Kinship", undated (Box 9)
  - Forward "Sacred Legacy" by NSM for a book of Edward Curtis's photographs, undated (Box 9)
  - Script to "Ancient Roots, Modern Medicine" -- NSM narrator., undated (Box 9)
  - Transcript of an interview of NSM by Nancy Bunge, dated January 8, 2004, circa 2000s (Box 9)
  - Mail and postcards dating to the 1970s, one from Anne 1971, circa 1970s (Box 9)
  - Photocopies and newspaper clippings of media coverage of the 2003 Achievement Summit in Washington D.C. plus travel information to the summit, circa 2000s (Box 9)
  - Folder of 5x7 photographic prints of artwork; two sheets of slide with artwork and letters from "Cowboys and Indians" regarding the artwork, undated (Box 9)
  - Group photograph with NSM dated 2003; contact prints of NS; six 7x10 photographic portraits of NSM dated 1995 and 2001; Contact prints of NSM; labels to photographs written by NSM; 4x6 photographic prints; Envelope filled with contact prints of NSM portraits, folder filled with 4x6 photographic prints of NSM and events, circa 2000s (Box 9)
  - Article by NSM Nov. 26, 1972 pasted on a block of wood, circa 1970s (Box 9)
  - Color photocopies of magazine articles relating to cradleboards; "Cradleboard Project: Introduction" by NSM; The Buffalo Trust information regarding the Cradleboard Teaching Project, 1998; Buffalo trust badge, circa 1990s (Box 10)
  - Correspondence with Brown University Haffenreffer Museum of Anthropology regarding a cradle exhibit and catalogue project, 1999; "The cradleboard project introduction by NSM; "Gifts of Love Cradleboards: by Marcelle Sharron Ahtone Harjo; Interviews with cradleboard makers (interview between Barbara Hail and Jim Arterberry, 1998) "Beyond Worth: The Legacy of Guohaddle's Cradles" by Ray C. Doyah; "The Rowell Cradle Collection" Everett R Rhoades; "Comanche Cradleboard" Juanita Pahdopony; "Guohaddle: Master Beadworker and Dradle-Maker" Beatice A. Smith; "I Remember How They Did That" Jacob Ahtone; "Gifts of Pride and Love" Vanessa Jennings, circa 1990s (Box 10)
  - Papers and work for the Cradleboard Project in 1998 including "Guohaddle: Master Beadworker and Cradle-Maker" Beatrice Smith; "Timeless Treasures" Ray Doyan; Chart of descendants of Ahpeatone; National Endowment for the Humanities proposal for the Cradleboard exhibit; Brown University Haffenreffer Museum of Anthropology plan for exhibition; Barbara A. Hail Curriculum Vitae; Notes from Nov. 16 1979 exhibit planning committee; 4x6 photographs of meetings; genealogical charts; photocopies of pictures (for exhibit?); Narration for IAIA Museum Video, circa 1990s (Box 10)
  - Correspondence with the Haffenreffer Museum of Anthropology regarding the Cradleboard exhibit. 1997-1998, circa 1990s (Box 10)
  - Oklahoma Book Awards booklet 2000, two 4x6 pictures, two buttons for organizations and societies, circa 2000s (Box 10)
  - Pamphlets for an art show showcasing Darren Vigil Great the Peyton Wright, August 1-Sept. 3 1997 (8 copies); Darren Vigil Gray Artist's statement; List of Darren Vigil Gray exhibitions; Photocopies of media coverage of Darren Vigil Gray's work; folder with slides of Gray's work and pamphlets from his art shows and media coverage of the artist, undated (Box 10)
  - Contracts, correspondence and agreements concerning a French publication of "Children of the Sun" many of the papers are in French and are dated 2002-2003, circa 2000s (Box 10)
  - La Maison De L'Aube by NSM, undated (Box 10)
  - Correspondence between Trish Crapo and NSM regarding Crapo's poems and writing in 1999, circa 1990s (Box 10)
  - Letter to Brian Dennehy March 6 1999, circa 1990s (Box 10)
  - Letter and a card from Daniela, circa 1990s (Box 10)
  - Correspondence with Art Gallahor as well as some of Art's poems, circa 1990s (Box 10)
  - Email from Daniele Laruella in France August 2000, circa 2000s (Box 10)
  - Emails from Richard Leakey Nov. 1999, circa 1990s (Box 10)
  - Correspondence regarding "Sing with the Heart of the Bear: Fusions of Native American and Canonical poetry 1890-1999" with an outline and some work written, undated (Box 10)
  - Letters and newspaper clippings about Charles and Beth Miller (neighbors to NSM?), undated (Box 10)
  - Letter of nomination for the Margaret Mead Selection Committee by NSM nominating Nancy Marie Mithlo for the award, undated (Box 10)
  - Correspondence to Jim Moore, undated (Box 10)
  - Letter to NSM from Simon Ortiz about a magazine special edition which Ortiz is editing. The letter asks NSM to contribute, dated May 29, 1998, circa 1990s (Box 10)
  - Poems by Meir Z. Ribalow. One entitled "The Bear" is dedicated to NSM, undated (Box 10)
  - Postcard with a WPA poster of Devil's Tower National Monument to NSM from Ken Roemer with a larger photograph as well, undated (Box 10)
  - New Years card from Tazewell Thompson to NSM, 1998, circa 1990s (Box 10)
  - Letter from the American Literary Translators Association with attached contact information for Carolyn Tipton, 1998, circa 1990s (Box 10)
  - Program from Morris King Udall's memorial service, 1998, circa 1990s (Box 10)
  - Letter from NSM to Elie and Marion, April 1999, circa 1990s (Box 10)
  - Correspondence, meeting minutes and updates for the Native American Preparatory School (NAPS) in the year 2000, circa 2000s (Box 10)
  - Email correspondence with Alan Wilson 1999, circa 1990s (Box 10)
  - Contracts, travel itinerary and correspondence regarding a presentation a the Diversity Learning Center Grand Rapids Community College, in Grand Rapids, MI, October 8, 2003, circa 2000s (Box 10)
  - Letter to Stewart Udall from NSM regarding the memorial service for Lee Udall with poems and clippings attached, May 2002, circa 2000s (Box 10)
  - Email to Diane with the subject line "Photographs at U.S. Army Milt. History Institute, Carlisle Barracks, PA." June, 2000; folder of material from the U.S. Army War College; Folder of material from Carlisle pow wow, circa 2000s (Box 10)
  - American Indian College Fund letter to NSM about the 6th annual Flame of Hope Gala, requesting support, 2001, circa 2000s (Box 10)
  - Booklet "The Nuclear-Free Future Award: In the Spirit of the World Uranium Hearing, Los Alamos 1999: Stewart Udall recipient; paperwork for the First Nations Development Institute; United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization, circa 1990s (Box 10)
  - Correspondence, agreements and press releases regarding the American Indian Ritual Object Repatriation Foundation and the Association on American Indian Affairs seemingly regarding a return which NSM was asked to be present; There is also a folder of the organizations newsletter "News and Notes" and information on "Mending the Circle" about repatriation, undated (Box 10)
  - Letter from Americans for Indian Opportunity thanking NSM for his support, June 2000, circa 2000s (Box 10)
  - Personal notes and letters, along with a piece of bark with a note written on it; Pamphlets and information on the Playwrights Project at Healing Springs, NC which NSM participated in, 1999, circa 1990s (Box 10)
  - Newsletters from the Augusta Military Academy Alumni Association, 2000, circa 2000s (Box 10)
  - Memorial papers for Doris Aitson, undated (Box 10)
  - Correspondence between NSM and Dick Bridgeman regarding photographs, 1999, circa 1990s (Box 10)
  - Cards and poems from David Born, undated (Box 10)
  - Oklahoma Arts Institute: A Celebration of the Spirit; An Anthology documenting an arts institute at Quartz Mountain with families of victims and survivors of the Oklahoma City Bombing, undated (Box 10)
  - Correspondence, agreements, letters, pamphlets and information packets pertaining to a National Museum of the American Indian film which NSM narrated and contributed to brainstorming session., undated (Box 10)
  - Letter from the Scottsdale Museum of Contemporary Art dated Sept.. 2, 1998 thanking NSM for lending artwork to a show "Fritz Sholder: Icon & Apparitions 1957-1997" with a spiral bound listing of the artwork., circa 1990s (Box 10)
  - Various greeting cards and letters to NSM, undated (Box 10)
  - Index cards with handwritten notes and addresses and a letter regarding the Sovereignty Symposium in June 1999, circa 1990s (Box 10)
  - Letter from the Kiowa Tribe of Oklahoma Enrollment Specialist, Vena M. Beaver regarding elders payment, 2000, circa 2000s (Box 10)
  - Correspondence with Betty Price including her recommendation that NSM receive the National Medal of Arts, 2000, circa 2000s (Box 10)
  - Letters and cards from Ann Simmons Alspaugh, one card in an envelope contains 4x6 photographs of NSM speaking and signing books at an event; also included are letters concerning Ms. Alspaugh's donation and support of the Buffalo Trust, undated (Box 10)